William Sharp

Software Engineering Leader

☆ 4490 Ramsey Rd, Oxford MI 48371
♦ 248.701.6591
⋈ wsharp07@gmail.com
O github.com/wsharp07

Executive Summary

Acquired over thirteen years of experience as a Full Stack Software Engineer, Software Engineering Leader, and I.T. Leader. Self-starter with a breadth of knowledge from working in all fields of the development process. Depth of experience includes obtaining requirements from customers and creating functional documentation, to leading a development team. Executed a broad set of skills from the operations field, including continuous integration, release management, and systems administration. Analyze problems from many different perspectives and jump in wherever help is needed. Recognized as a key contributor in both the business development and software development processes.

Areas of Expertise

Coaching & Mentoring	Team Development	Software Development Lifecycle
Software Architecture	Technical infrastructure	Process Improvement
Problem Solving	Decision Making	Lean Methodologies

Professional History

Staff Software Engineer - Rocket Auto, Detroit, MI

August 2021 - Present

Responsible for the engineering solutions and architecture to support key company initiatives. Set engineering standards for the company and mentored existing and new engineers. Championed our post incident process by driving actionable outcomes to continuously improve our organization. Responsible for all our code bases written primarily in Typescript and React.

Key Accomplishments

- Engineering lead for a key project to improve our SEO and website performance by moving to Next.js
 - o Resulted in improved SEO and performance measured by our organic search traffic and Core Web Vitals.
- Implemented Docker and NPM caching strategies to speed up our CI/CD pipelines in Azure DevOps
 - o Cut the time to deploy in half
- Implemented a monorepo strategy using Nx to allow our engineer team to quickly deploy shared libraries.
- Worked with another staff engineer to design our engineering interview process from the ground up.

Software Engineering Team Leader - Rocket Mortgage, Detroit, MI

May 2018 - August 2021

Led a cross-functional technology team with ten direct reports. A servant leader who takes pride in mentoring team members through regular individualized coaching. Certified Scrum Master who guides the team in agile practices and helps the team maintain efficiency by removing roadblocks. Lives the DevOps mindset by championing a solid CI/CD pipeline, frequent delivery of business value, minimal handoffs, and a collaboration between operations and development team members.

Key Accomplishments

- Drove a training initiative across 15+ teams to level up our knowledge of DevOps practices
- Championed a software community within the Release Train to foster communication and collaboration
- Empowered team members to be accountable and take control of their product delivery process
- Mentored non-software development team members to learn software skills to improve in their role
- Built a team to focus on a new strategic business direction

Principal Developer/Team Lead – ARC Healthcare Technologies, Orion, MI May 2011 – May 2018

Initially employed as a Technical Project Manager, but quickly elevated to Software Engineer due to a strong passion and talent for software development. Innovative critical thinking and drive quickly resulted in a position as Product Lead for the ASP.NET Web Forms application. Orchestrated numerous projects, such as migrating the ASP.NET Web Forms application to ASP.NET MVC, transitioning from TFSVC to GitHub, and implementing agile practices.

Team Leader

Served as Project Lead on several new software features, coordinated key client projects, led team members, and provided valuable input to the company as it continued to expand.

- Served as key decision maker for software development practices and technologies for the company
- Coordinated with clients to obtain requirements, created product requirement documents, and generated functional documents for developers
- Communicated with developers to ensure understanding of functional documents
- Improved team communication and operations by implementing Slack company wide

Principle Software Developer

As a point of pride, developed and own the company web application. Mentored new software developers. Additionally, co-managed the direction of the software development process over the course of the past six years.

- Improved the speed of software delivery by 150 percent
- Full Stack .NET Developer (C#)

- Introduced GitHub Flow to improve the software development process
- Key contributor to our N-tier software architecture

Lead DevOps Engineer

Leader and organizer of all network and systems infrastructure. Implemented agile practices and continuous integration for the software team. Sole maintainer of all development processes and standards.

- Implemented JIRA and SCRUM processes to replace an aging and inefficient waterfall-like process
- Employed Confluence to hold all developer documentation as well as client facing documentation
- Created software design standards and coding conventions to standardize the company software
- Instrumental in the migration from no source control, to TFS, finally to GitHub
- Implemented TeamCity for Continuous Integration and Octopus Deploy for Continuous Delivery
- Setup a PF Sense based Firewall system and an OpenVPN remote access solution
- Established Active Directory to manage company users, permissions, and workstations
- Provisioned several Hypervisors using VMWare ESXi 5 and Hyper-V 2016
- Designed and implemented wired and wireless network infrastructure for the site

Technical Project Manager – Media Genesis, Troy, MI 2011

June 2009 - May

Progressed from an I.T. internship to a Technical Project Manager in under a year. Brought multiple projects in under budget and ahead of schedule. Influenced technical decisions in the business. Facilitated communication between the customers and the I.T. Department.

- Gathered requirements from customers to determine I.T. services needed
- Worked with I.T. team members to facilitate and participate in onsite installations of servers, along with provisioning of computer hardware
- Managed Debian and CentOS servers in an offsite datacenter
- Setup and managed websites using Apache and Nginx
- Functioned as Technical Lead in service desk support for roughly 30 on-site users
- Repaired and upgraded an extensive server cluster
- Ran network and telecom cables throughout the building

Core Competencies

Business	I.T./DevOps	Software Tools	Languages/Frameworks
Azure DevOps	Linux (Debian, CentOS)	Visual Studio 2012- 2019	C#, .NET Core
Microsoft Office	Windows (XP-10, Server 2003-2019)	IntelliJ Idea	Java, SpringBoot
Microsoft Visio	Azure, AWS	VS Code	JavaScript, Typescript, Node.js, NestJS, Next.js
Confluence	Windows Embedded/IoT Enterprise	SSMS	HTML/CSS
Trello	TeamCity/Jenkins/Circle CI	Jira	SQL
Zendesk	SQL Server 2008-2019	Git	WCF, SignalR
SharePoint	SSRS 2008-2014	TFS, Azure DevOps	Service Stack

Formal Education

BS: Computer Science (3.5 GPA)

Lawrence Technological University, Southfield, MI

BS: Information Technology (3.5 GPA)

Lawrence Technological University, Southfield, MI

Projects

Innovative projects and personal creations. Most hosted on my GitHub account.

K9-forms

Developed ReactJS form printing application for a non-profit rescue league

pc-prox-console

C++ console application for interacting with

pcProx card readers

Stargate VueJS interface and .NET Core API for uploading files to Azure storage

DHCPSharp Simple C# DHCP server